Guide to the James Augustus Thomas papers, 1895-1988, bulk 1914-1940 RL.01289
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
James Augustus Thomas papers
1895-1988, bulk 1914-1940
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Thomas, J. A. (James Augustus), 1862-1940
RL.01289
86 Linear Feet 65 boxes
The papers of tobacco industrialist and philanthropist James Augustus Thomas (1862-1940) primarily concern his commercial and diplomatic dealings in East Asia, and the opening of the tobacco market in China and other countries in the early 20th century. Materials include many boxes of correspondence, print and ephemeral materials, and photographs. Correspondents include Herbert Hoover, Robert Lansing, Theodore Roosevelt, William Howard Taft, and Sun Yat-sen. Includes materials relating to U.S.-China foreign and economic relations; the marketing of U.S. cigarettes in Asia; the British-American Tobacco Company; domestic policies and financial development in China; political events in East Asia and Europe; and philanthropy in China, including Thomas' efforts to bring Chinese students to Duke University. There are also some personal letters and three audiocassettes of an oral interview with Dorothy Read Thomas, Thomas's widow, with a typed transcript; interview topics include her life in China and St. Petersburg, Russia in the 1920s.
Arrangement
Arranged in two series: Correspondence and Papers.
Biographical Note
James Augustus Thomas, tobacco merchant and philanthropist, was born March 6, 1862 in Rockingham County, NC to Henry Evans Thomas and Cornelia Carolina Jones Thomas. At the age of 10, he started working in a tobacco warehouse and in 1881, he graduated from Eastman National Business College in Poughkeepsie, NY. He began working at the British-American Tobacco Company, Ltd. at its inception in 1902 and by 1904, he was serving as Managing Director in China. Thomas is considered the person largely responsible for introducing American cigarettes to China and other countries. He founded the Chinese-American Bank of Commerce and two schools for Chinese children. All in all he spent over 25 years in China.
He retired from the BATC in 1922 and settled in White Plains, New York, where he lived for the rest of his life. His association with the Dukes in the tobacco industry culminated in a relationship with Duke University. In 1928, Thomas donated his Far East Library to the university. He was a member of the Board of Trustees and also served as Chair of the Duke Memorial Association, which built the Memorial Chapel within Duke Chapel, where the remains of Washington Duke, James B. Duke and Benjamin N. Duke are interred.
In 1918, Thomas married Anna Branson who died 7 months later. In 1922, he married Dorothy Quincy Hancock Read on Nov. 21, 1922. Her father, Sheridan Pitt Read, was the American Consul in Tientsin in the early 20th century. They had two children: James Augustus Thomas, Jr. and Eleanor Lansing Thomas.
Thomas was the author of two books: A Pioneer Tobacco Merchant in the Orient (1928) and Trailing Trade a Million Miles (1931).
He died in 1940 in White Plains, New York.
Access Restrictions
Audiovisual materials are closed to use; listening copies may be required for access.
Conditions Governing Access
Access is partially restricted. Negatives are closed to use; photographic prints of the images are present in the collection.
Provenance
The James Augustus Thomas papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 1952-1953, 1989, 1999, 2001, 2013, 2014.
Collection Overview
The papers of James Augustus Thomas comprise many folders of correspondence, printed material, and other papers (chiefly 1914-1940), related to his commercial and diplomatic dealings in East Asia and the opening of the tobacco market in China and other countries. Correspondents include Herbert Hoover, Robert Lansing, Theodore Roosevelt, William Howard Taft, and Sun Yat-sen. There are also some personal letters.
The materials document U.S.-China foreign and economic relations; the marketing of U.S. cigarettes in Asia; the British-American Tobacco Company; U.S.-Chinese trade; domestic policies and financial development in China; political events in East Asia and Europe; American foreign policy in East Asia (1920s-1930s); and philanthropy in China, including Thomas' efforts to bring Chinese students to Duke University and other North Carolina institutions.
Printed materials in the collection include reports, economic summaries, essays, conference programs, memos, and ephemera such as admission cards, tickets, and pamphlets. Some materials relate to the World's Fair in New York, and a visit by a Chinese delegation to New York in 1915, illustrated with photographs.
Additions to the collection include three letters pertaining or written to son, Jimmy, by his parents, gelatin silver photographs and a few negatives, and three audiocassettes of an oral interview (by Duke Professor Emeritus Richard Watson) with Dorothy Read Thomas, widow of James A. Thomas, which include a typed transcript. Interview topics include her life in China and Petrograd (now St. Petersburg, Russia) where she taught school briefly; and the social life and customs in Bejing and Shanghai after she married Thomas in 1922.
There are also negative microfilm reels of the series "China Through Western Eyes: Part 3, The Papers of J.A. Thomas c.1905-1923." Positive reels have been sent to the microfilm department.
Chinese -- United States; Chinese students -- United States -- History; Cigarette industry -- East Asia -- History; Tobacco industry -- China -- History; Tobacco industry -- East Asia -- History; Tobacco industry -- United States -- History; China -- Commerce -- United States; China -- Economic policy; China -- Photographs; China -- Politics and government -- 1912-1949; China -- Social life and customs; East Asia -- Foreign relations -- United States; East Asia -- Politics and government; Saint Petersburg (Russia) -- Description and travel; Shanghai (China) -- Social life and customs; United States -- Commerce -- China; United States -- Foreign relations -- China; United States -- Foreign relations -- East Asia; Audiocassettes; Black-and-white photographs; Gelatin silver prints; Microfilms; Thomas, Dorothy Q.; Sun, Yat-sen, 1866-1925; Taft, William H. (William Howard), 1857-1930; Lansing, Robert, 1864-1928; Duke University -- History; Hoover, Herbert, 1874-1964; Roosevelt, Theodore; British American Tobacco Company; Thomas, J. A. (James Augustus), 1862-1940; Watson, Richard
- Correspondence, 1895-1988, bulk 1914-1940; 46 boxes
  - 1895-1915 May (also includes information folder) (Box 1)
  - 1915 June-Dec. (Box 2)
  - 1916 March, 1920 (Box 3)
  - 1920 Apr.-Sept. (Box 4)
  - 1920 Oct.-1921 Mar. (Box 5)
  - 1921 Apr.-Aug. (Box 6)
  - 1921 Sept.-1922 Jan. (Box 7)
  - 1922 Feb.-May (Box 8)
  - 1922 June-Dec. (Box 9)
  - 1923 (Box 10)
  - 1924 Jan.-Oct. (Box 11)
  - 1924 Nov.-1925 Aug. (Box 12)
  - 1925 Sept.-1926 Mar. (Box 13)
  - 1926 Apr.-1927 Feb. (Box 14)
  - 1927-1928 Mar. (Box 15)
  - 1928 Apr.-Nov. (Box 16)
  - 1928 Dec.-1929 June (Box 17)
  - 1929 July-Dec. (Box 18)
  - 1930 Jan.-May (Box 19)
  - 1930 June-Dec. (Box 20)
  - 1931 Jan.-May (Box 21)
  - 1931 June-Oct. (Box 22)
  - 1931 Nov.-1932 Apr. (Box 23)
  - 1932 May-Nov. (Box 24)
  - 1932 Dec.-1933 Apr. (Box 25)
  - 1933 May-Sept. (Box 26)
  - 1933 Oct.-1934 Feb. (Box 27)
  - 1934 Mar.-June (Box 28)
  - 1934 July-Nov. (Box 29)
  - 1934 Dec.-1935 May (Box 30)
  - 1935 June-Dec. (Box 31)
  - 1936 Jan.-Apr. (Box 32)
  - 1936 May-Sept. (Box 33)
  - 1936 Oct.-1937 Feb. (Box 34)
  - 1937 Mar.-June (Box 35)
  - 1937 July-Oct. (Box 36)
  - 1937 Nov.-1938 Jan. 14 (Box 37)
  - 1938 Jan. 15-Mar. (Box 38)
  - 1938 Apr.-June 17 (Box 39)
  - 1938 June 18-Sept. (Box 40)
  - 1938 Oct.-1939 Jan. (Box 41)
  - 1939 Feb.-June (Box 42)
  - 1939 July-Dec. (Box 43)
  - 1940 Jan.-June (Box 44)
  - 1940 July-1941 Jan. (Box 45)
  - Thomas family correspondence, 1948-1988 (Box 45)
  - Duplicates, 1922, 1940 Oct. (Box 46)
- Papers, 1900-1985, bulk 1900-1940; 17 boxes
  Scope and Contents
  Series includes many topical files in original alphabetical order within folders, as well as print and ephemeral materials, and photographs. All materials relate to Thomas' time in East Asia, his philanthropic work in China, the tobacco industry in East Asia, and U.S. economic and diplomatic relations in East Asia. There is also an oral history interview with Dorothy Thomas on her life in China and in Petrograd (St. Petersburg) during the 1920s. Negative microfilm reels contain images from the Thomas papers.
  - Papers, undated (Box 47)
  - Papers, undated (Box 48)
  - Addresses and Writings; Thomas and others, mostly printed (Box 49)
  - Banks; British American Tobacco Company (Box 50)
  - British American Tobacco Company Bulletin; Chambers of Commerce (Box 51)
  - Charities, various, and the China International Famine Relief Commission (Box 52)
  - China Monthly Trade Reports; Church Committee for China Relief; Executive Committee Minutes (Box 53)
  - Church Committee for China Relief; Various clubs and societies (Box 54)
  - Consumer publications; Council on Foreign Relations (Box 55)
  - Duke University; Hospitals (Box 56)
  - Imperial Tobacco Company; Institute of Pacific Relations (Box 57)
  - Insurance companies; Schools, colleges, universities (Box 58)
  - Shanghai American School; Tennessee Valley Authority (Box 59)
  - Tobacco industry, various papers; Yenching University (Box 60)
  - Printed materials and ephemera, circa 1914-1938 (Box 61)
    Folders contain printed materials collected by James Thomas, and include conference and meeting programs, reports, essays, analyses, and pamphlets, all relating to U.S. diplomatic and economic relations with East Asian countries, especially Japan and China, from about 1914 to 1938. Other topics relate to concerns about political events and global conflict in the late 1920s. Also includes ephemera such as programs and cards, with some relating to the New York World's Fair. A souvenir program with large mounted black-and-white photographs commemorates the visit of a Chinese delegation to New York in 1915.
  - Interview with Dorothy Q. Thomas: transcript and 3 audiocassettes, 1985 Dec. 16-17, and letters to James A. Thomas, Jr., 1938-1939 (Box 62)
    Conditions Governing Access
    Original recordings are closed to use; listening copies may be requested in advance.
  - Negative microfilm reels of the series "China Through Western Eyes: Part 3, The Papers of J. A. Thomas c.1905-1923", 1980s? (Box 63)
  - Framed Chinese landscape of woven fabric, undated (Box 64)
  - Photographs, 1910s-1940s (Box 65)
    Includes albumen card photographs; a page from a scrapbook with some mounted photographs; early gelatin silver prints, some of which are of James Thomas in China; larger modern copy prints, one of Dorothy Thomas, and one of James Thomas, seated, dressed as a mandarin, flanked by two Chinese smoking cigarettes; and eight copy negatives (safety film) of the smaller photographs.
    Negatives are closed to use; photographic prints are present.
- Oversize Materials
  - Clippings, 1926-1932 (Oversize-folder 1)